Finding Aid for Jean Paul Slusser papers, 1905-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jean Paul Slusser papers 1905-1978
Slusser, Jean Paul, 1886-
85402 Aa 2 AC
Artist, art critic, director of the University of Michigan Art Museum. Scrapbooks with clippings of Ann Arbor News art reviews, scrapbook, 1905-1907, concerning University of Michigan student life, topical files relating to his interest in art and cultural organizations, original scripts of lectures and radio talks.
2 linear feet
2 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection came from Professor Slusser (donor no. 4631 ) in 1981. A smaller portion came from the University of Michigan Museum of Art (donor no. 3195 ).
The collection is open to research.
Jean Paul Slusser was born December 15, 1886 in Wauseon, Ohio. He received his A.B. degree from the University of Michigan in 1909 and his A.M. in 1911. He also studied at the University of Munich (1909-1910), the Museum of Fine Arts School in Boston (1913-1915), the Art Students League of New York (summers 1914-1917), and the Hans Hofmann Schule in Munich (1924-1925).
Slusser taught drawing, painting, and architecture during summers at the University of Michigan (1921, 1922, 1925-1926). In 1927 he was appointed assistant professor of painting and drawing. Prior to coming to the University of Michigan on a permanent basis, Slusser was art critic for the Boston Herald (1913-1915), a free lance painter and designer in New York City (1919-1921) and assistant art critic for the New York Herald (1921-1923).
In 1936, Slusser was promoted to associate professor and then in 1944 to full professor. In addition, in 1946, he was named acting director of the University of Michigan Art Museum. In 1947, he was named director, serving until his retirement in 1957. He remained active reviewing art exhibitions for the Ann Arbor News, 1963-1978.
Not only a teacher, Slusser was also an accomplished painter whose works were exhibited and widely collected. He won many prizes for his work and was the recipient of many awards. Professor Slusser died in May 1981.
The Slusser papers document only portions of this artist/critic's life. The majority of the collection consists of scrapbooks containing his art review columns for the Ann Arbor News. These were written in the period of his retirement, 1963 to 1978. There is also one scrapbook from his years as a student at the University of Michigan, 1905-1907. The remainder of the collection consists of such personal materials as a diary he kept of a trip to Europe in 1909 when he went to study in Munich, a selection of some of his lectures and radio talks, and miscellaneous topical files relating to art and artists. Of interest is a series of letters written to his brother Herbert and letters received from artist William H. Littlefield.
Subjects:
Art.; Artists.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Museum of Art.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1901-1910.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Galleries and museums.; Art.; Art and Architecture Building (University of Michigan); Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Exhibitions.; Galleries and museums--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Prettyman House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Slusser, Jean Paul, 1886-1981; Slusser Gallery.
Contributors:
Adams, James P. (James Pickwell), 1895-1969.; Adams, Randolph Greenfield, 1892-1951.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Scrapbooks
  - Scrapbook concerning University of Michigan student life 1905-1907 (Box 1)
  - Personal scrapbook 1913-1967 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor News Art Review columns
    - 1963 October-1966 March (Box 1)
    - 1966 March-1968 February (Box 1)
    - 1968 March-1969 November (Box 1)
    - 1969 November-1971 July (Box 1)
    - 1971 July-1973 July (Box 1)
    - 1973 July-1976 July (Box 1)
  - 1976 July-1977 October (Volume 1)
  - 1977 July-1978 September (Volume 2)
- Topical files
  - Adams (James P.) correspondence 1948-1950 (Box 2)
  - Adams (Randolph) correspondence 1946-1951 (Box 2)
  - American Association of Museum panel discussion 1955 (Box 2)
  - Ann Arbor Art Association (Box 2)
  - Exhibit honoring Slusser -- sign describing exhibit (Box 2)
  - Littlefield, William H., letters from 1950-1951, 1954-1957, 6 folders (Box 2)
    (Littlefield was prominent abstract expressionist painter)
  - Michigan Watercolor Society (Box 2)
  - Museum of Art Friends (Box 2)
  - Nuckles (Charles R.) paper on Michigan Art and Artists (Box 2)
  - President's club (Box 2)
  - Print collecting (Box 2)
- Other materials
  - Original scripts of lectures, radio talks, and other discourses (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, articles, and memorabilia (Box 2)
  - Letters written to his brother Herbert 1968-1973, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Diary of trip to Europe, 1909 (Box 2)
    (original and transcript of diary)
  - Photographs
    - Slusser Gallery, Art and Architecture Building (Box 2)
    - Opening of the Slusser Gallery 1975 March 09 (Box 2)
    - Portraits, studio, and exterior of H. G. Prettyman House in Ann Arbor (Box 2)
      (now site of U-M Dental Building)